<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter, containing some reflections, on a discourse called Good advice to the Church of England, &amp;c. and upon three letters from a gentlemen in the country to his friend in London about the repeal of the penal laws and tests</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09390</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">62369429</idno>
  <idno type="VID">187986</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248530399</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1357A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219067</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">62369429</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09390)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 187986)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2851:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter, containing some reflections, on a discourse called Good advice to the Church of England, &amp;c. and upon three letters from a gentlemen in the country to his friend in London about the repeal of the penal laws and tests</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and last leaf torn with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Penn, William, 1644-1718. --  Good advice to the Church of England, Roman Catholick, and Protestant dissenter.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:187986:1"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A LETTER, Containing some</hi> Reflections, <hi>on a</hi> Discourse, <hi>called</hi> Good Advice to the Church of England, <hi>&amp;c. and upon</hi> three Letters from a Gentleman in the Country to his Friend in London, <hi>about the</hi> Repeal <hi>of the</hi> Penal Laws <hi>and</hi> Tests.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have at last procured a sight of the Book stiled <hi>Good Advice to the Church of England, Roman Catholick and Protestant Dissenter;</hi> and of the <hi>three Letters from a Gentleman in the Countrey to his Friend in London;</hi> which as they are written by one and the same person, so he endeavoures in all of them to make it appear to be the <hi>Duty, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> and <hi>Interest</hi> of the Parties mentioned, to <hi>abolish the Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Tests.</hi> Now tho' I'm day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in expectation of seeing such an Answer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to those Papers, as will both give the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor cause to wish he had been otherway's imploy'd when he wrote them, and make the Court Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction asham'd of the Elogies they have heapt upon him for his service; yet it may not be amiss in the mean time, to shew in a very few pages, that 'tis not any considerable strength in those Discourses, which hath given them a Reputation, but the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of some to have every thing accounted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>answerable that is published in favour of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signes, and the folly and weakness of others, which makes them believe that to be nervous, in whose success they imagine their ease to be wrapt up and involved.</p>
            <p>I think it is universally acknowledged, and I'm sure it can be demonstratively proved, that they are written by a <hi>Quaker;</hi> and this ought to render us jealous both of the motives influencing unto it, and of the end to which they are designed to be subservient. For <hi>first,</hi> the affinity of several of the <hi>Religions Principles</hi> of that <hi>Party,</hi> with some of the material <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the <hi>Romish Church,</hi> may notwithstanding the Charity which we retain to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the bulk of them, make us justly apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive, that one or more of their Leaders are inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely in the Interest of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> For as the Popish Emissaries know how to put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into all shapes, for the increasing and height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning divisions among <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>estants,</hi> and for the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing as well as supplanting of our Religion; so the design promoted in the foresaid Papers, of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying all the <hi>Legal Fences</hi> against <hi>Popery,</hi> and of letting the <hi>Papists</hi> into the <hi>Legislative</hi> and whole <hi>Executive</hi> Power of the Government, gives the world too much ground to suspect out of whose mint and forge writings of this stamp and mettle do proceed. <hi>Secondly,</hi> It should not a little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to augment our Jealousie, that they who without being false to their Religious Tenets, can not join to assist <hi>Protestants,</hi> in case the <hi>Papists</hi> should attempt to cut our Throats, or endeavour to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose their Religion upon the Nation by Military force; should of all men study to overthrow that Security which we have by the <hi>Test</hi> Laws, whose whole tendency is only to prevent the <hi>Papists,</hi> from getting into a condition to extirpate our Religion, and destroy us. Is it not enough, that they have rob'd the Kingdom of the Aid of so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as they have leavened with their Doctrine, in case the King upon despairing to establish <hi>Popery</hi> by a <hi>Parliament,</hi> should imploy his <hi>Janizaries</hi> to compel us to receive it, and should set upon the converting <hi>Protestants</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> in the way that the <hi>French Monarch</hi> hath converted the <hi>Hugenots;</hi> but that over and above this, they should be doing all they c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, to deprive us of all the Legal Security, whereby we may be preserved from the Power of the Papists? Surely 'twere not Charit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and good Nature, but stupidity and folly, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o suspect the tendency of such a design, when we find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued and carried on by a person that stiles himself a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then when besides this we find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Mr. William Pen,</hi> who is the <hi>Author</hi> of those <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ers,</hi> and the great Instrument in advancing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, we have the more cause to suspect. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistruous thing at the bottom of it. For <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st▪</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is under those Obligations to His Majesty, which as they may put a biaz upon his Understanding, so they afford ground enough to <hi>Protestants</hi> to look upon him no otherway's than as one Retained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them. 'Twas through his present Majesties Intercession with the late King, that he obtained th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Proprietorship</hi> of <hi>Pensilvania,</hi> and from his Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that he had the <hi>Propriety</hi> of <hi>three</hi> whole <hi>Counties</hi> bordering upon it superadded thereunto. And as this can not be but a strong Obligation upon so greateful person as Mr. <hi>Pen,</hi> why he should ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually serve the King, and make his will in a very great degree the measure of his actings; so it ought to be an Inducement to others to be the more jealous of all he say's, and not to surrender
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:187986:2"/> themselves too easily either to his Magisterial Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates upon the one hand, or to his smooth Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries upon the other. He must have either laid a mighty merit upon the two Royal Brothers of both whose Religion we are at last convinced, or he must have come under Obligations, of doing them very considerable service in reference to that which they were most fond of compassing; otherway's we have little cause to think, that he would have been singled out from all the rest of the Kingdom, to be made the object of so special favour and of so eminent liberality. For tho' there might be a debt owing to his Father Sr. <hi>William Pen,</hi> yet they must be extreamly weak who conceive there was no other motive to the forementioned Donation, save Honor and Justice in the two Royal Brothers for having it discharged. Seeing many of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest Families in <hi>England,</hi> who had spent their Blood, and wasted their Estates in fighting for the Crown, while Sr. <hi>William Pen</hi> was all along in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gadged against it, were not only left without all kind of Compensation, for what they had emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently acted, and as eminently suffered in behalf of the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> but could never get to be reim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bursed one farthing of the vast Summs, which they had lent the late King and his Father upon the Security of the Royal Faith. <hi>Secondly, Mr. Pen</hi> hath too far detected himself in these very Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses, not to give us ground to suspect what they are calculated for, and whereunto they are subser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient. For besides his justifying the Kings turning so many Gentlemen of the Church of <hi>England</hi> out of all Office and Imploy, by saying, <hi>they are not fit to be trusted who are out of the Kings Interest;</hi> he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tells us, that <hi>the King being mortal, it is not good sense, that he should leave the power in those hands, that to his face shew their aversion to the Friends of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. (Letter first)?</hi> For as this implies no less, than that they ought to have the whole Legal and Military Power of the <hi>three Kingdoms</hi> put into their hands, that they may be in a condition to preclude the right Heir from Succession to the Crown, or prescribe such Laws to Her as they please, in case they should think fit to admit Her; so a very small measure of Understanding, will serve to instruct us, what the <hi>Papists</hi> esteem to be an <hi>aversion</hi> to them, and in what manner, had they the power in their hands, they think themselves obliged to treat us upon that account. And as we have had occasion to know too much of his <hi>Majesties</hi> Temper and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, as well as to whose Guidance he hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitely resigned himself, not to be sensible <hi>what</hi> he esteems his <hi>Interest;</hi> so we need no other evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence what it amounts unto <hi>to be in it,</hi> than the seeing so many displaced from all share in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministration, whose Quality gives them a Right, and their Abilities a fitness for the chiefest and most honorable Trusts; and whom as the King, by reason of their services to himself as well as the <hi>Crown,</hi> can not lay aside without the highest in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude; so their known Loyalty to his person, and zeal for the grandure of the <hi>Monarchy</hi> is such, that nothing could take them off from concurring in his Councels, and promoting his Designes, but the conviction they are under, of their tendency to the subversion of Religion, and the altering of the Legal Government.</p>
            <p>And as we have reason to suspect what the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said Papers are intended to promote, both upon the account of the <hi>Author's</hi> being <hi>Quaker,</hi> and because not only of the many Obligations he is under to His Majesty, but his being so intirely in his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest, as appears by his influence into Councils, the great stroke he hath in all Affairs, and from his being one of the Kings principal Confidents; so upon looking into those Discourses, we find several things obtruded on us for truth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed in order to wheedle and insnare us into an abrogation of the Laws enacted for our security, which to every ones knowledg are so palpably false, that we have all the ground that may be, both to question and suspect his sincerity, and to conclude that his Masters do not purpose to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine themselves within the bounds that he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to chalk out for them; and which he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes they shall be contented with for their allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For what can be remoter from Truth? than that the <hi>Test Laws were designed as a Preamble to the Bill of Exclusion,</hi> (as he phrases it <hi>Letter first</hi>) and that <hi>they were contrived to exclude the Duke of York from the Crown,</hi> (as he expresseth it P. 15. <hi>of his Good Advice,</hi> &amp;c.) when it is most certain that as the <hi>Test</hi> in 73. was made long before there were, or could be any thoughts of it, and was enacted by a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> against whose Loyalty there can be no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; so their was a clause in the last <hi>Test</hi> Act, by which it was provided that he should not be obliged to take it. Again what can be more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to experience, than that <hi>the King only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires ease for those of his Religion;</hi> (Good Adv. p. 44.) and that the <hi>Papists desire no more than a Toleration,</hi> and are willing upon <hi>those Terms to make a perpetual peace with the Church of England, (Good Advice p.</hi> 17.) For do we not dayly see Protestants turned out of all Places of Trust, Authority and Command; and Papists advanced into all Offices Military and Civil? Could the King have been contented with a Non-execution of the Laws against those of his Communion, and could they have been satisfied with such an Indulgence, and have modestly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved it: 'Tis not improbable but that such a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, would have so far prevailed upon the ingenuity and good nature of the generality of Protestants, that without needing to have been importuned, they would have repealed all the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> against <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> But the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods which have been pursued by his Majesty and them, shews both that they aim at no less than
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:187986:3"/> the Domination, and that we must be very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be deceived, if we either credit Mr. <hi>Pen</hi> or suffer our selves to be influenced by him, after his obtruding upon us for truths, matters which our very senses inable us to refute. It may justly make us question his sincerity, and beget a suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in all thinking people, of the sinistruous design these <hi>Papers</hi> are adapted unto, when we find him endeavouring to cajole the Nation to an abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Laws, by which our Religion and safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are secured, by telling us that <hi>the Kings word is enough for us to rely upon</hi> if they were gone, (<hi>Good Adv. p.</hi> 49.) and <hi>that he could easily pack a Parliament for Repealing them, if he did not seek a more lasting and more agreeable security to his Friends, (Letter third p.</hi> 12.) and that if they were abolished, <hi>'tis below the Glory of our King, to use way's so unlike the rest of his open and generous principles, as to endeavour to get a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament afterwards returned, that is not du'ly chosen (Letter second p.</hi> 15.) and that <hi>he is a Prince of that Honor, Conscience, and generous nature, as not by inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Rights of the Church of England, to become guilty of an injustice and irreligion, he hath so often, so solemnly and earnestly spoken against (Letter second p.</hi> 11) He must needs take us to be strangely unacquainted with the whole Tenor of the <hi>King</hi> Actings in <hi>England</hi> as well as in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to be persons of very weak understandings, and of an easie belief, if he think we are to be imposed upon, and decoy'd by such Topicks as these, to abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish the <hi>Tests;</hi> or that after what we have seen and felt contradictory to those <hi>Panegyricks,</hi> and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with those beautiful and lofty Characters fastned upon his Majesty, we should believe <hi>Mr Pen</hi> to mean nothing but well and honestly towards the <hi>Protestant</hi> Interest, in what he so earnestly sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciteth the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and the Dissenters in the forementioned <hi>Papers</hi> to concurr and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent unto.</p>
            <p>I do acknowledg, that what he hath said about Liberty due to men in matters of meer Religion, and by way of rebuke unto, and reflection upon the Wisdom and Justice of those that either are or have been for persecution, is very strong and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing; but I must withall add that it is all at this time very needless and impertinent. For the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is so sensible of the iniquity as well as folly of that method', that there is no ground to suspect She will ever be guilty of it for the future. They whom no Arguments could heretofore convert, the Court (whose Tools they were in that mischievous and Unchristian work, and by whom they were instigated to all the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities which they are now blamed for) by objecting it to them as their Reproach and disgrace, and by seeking to improve the resentments of those who had suffered by Penal Laws to become an united party with the <hi>Papists</hi> for their subversion, hath brought them at once to be asham'd of what they did, and to Resolutions of promoting all Christian Liberty for the time to come. And should there be any peevish and ill natur'd Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siasticks, who upon a turn of Affairs would be ready to reassume their former principles, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue their wonted course; we may be secure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all fear of their being succesful in it, not only by finding the majority as well as the more learned both of the dignified and inferior Clergy, unchangeably fixed and determined against it, but by having the whole Nobility and Gentry, and those Noble Princes whose Right it will be next to ascend the Throne, fully possessed with all the generous and Christian purposes we can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, of making provision for Liberty of Conscience by a Law. Nor can I forebear to subjoin how surprizing it ought to be to all <hi>Protestants,</hi> that while Mr. <hi>Pen</hi> expresseth so much charity for the <hi>Papists,</hi> he entertaineth so little for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> He would perswade us, that if the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> and <hi>Test Laws</hi> were abrogated, the <hi>Papists</hi> would be so far afterward from seeking to shake the Constitution of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> or from breaking in upon the Liberty that is now wouchsaved unto Dissenters, or from endeavouring to make their Religion national; that they would not only be <hi>contented with a bare Toleration,</hi> but that upon their enjoyment of ease by Law, <hi>they would turn good Countrymen, and come into the Interest of the Kingdom, (Lttter first.)</hi> Whereas at the same time he would have us believe, that all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testations of those in the Communion of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> for exercising moderation in time to come, are but the <hi>Language of their fear; that their Promises are not to be trusted; (Good Adv. p.</hi> 54) and that <hi>the Dissenters deserve to be begged for Fools,</hi> should they be satisfied with any less assurance, <hi>than the abolition of the Penal and Test Laws, (ibid. p.</hi> 55.) 'Tis enough not only to excite our jealousy, but to stirr up severer passions, to be told at a season when we know what the <hi>Catholicks</hi> are doing in <hi>France,</hi> and in most other places where they have any power, that the <hi>Papists through having burnt their fingers with persecution, may be grown so wise as to do so no more;</hi> and yet to have it asserted in the same Page, that they who can be prevailed upon to believe, <hi>that the Church of England is sorry for what She hath done, and that She will not be guilty of such a thing again, have little reason to quarrel at the unaccountableness of Transubstantiation. (Good Advice p.</hi> 8.) Nor is it becoming one who stiles himself a <hi>Protestant,</hi> no more than it is consistent with Truth, to extenuate our <hi>being scandal'd at the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity upon Protestants in France, by affirming that he can parralell some of the severst passages in that Kingdom, out of the Actions of some Members of the Church of England in cool Blood, (ibid. p</hi> 7.) And tho' I have all the kindness imaginable for Mr. <hi>Pen's</hi> person, and am loath to think otherway's of him as to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:187986:4"/> principles, than as his avowed profession discovers him; yet these and diverse passages more of that kind, together with the accession he must necessarily have had to the apprehension and imprisonment of Mr. <hi>Gray,</hi> &amp;c. for abandoning the <hi>Benedictine Order;</hi> are things I can neither recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile to the title he assumes, nor to his many Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses for Repealing the <hi>Test</hi> Laws. And to speak freely considering the Nature of our Laws against <hi>Papists,</hi> and that it was their manifold Treasons, and only our care to preserve our selves, that both gave the first rise unto them, and has ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitated their continuance; I know neither how to construe that Assertion of Mr. <hi>Pen's (Good Adv. p.</hi> 13.) that the <hi>Principle which the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland acts by, justifies the King of France and the Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> nor that other <hi>(Letter first) of there having been eight times more Laws made for ruining men for their Conscience, since the Church of England came to be the National Establishment, than were all the time that Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was in the Chair.</hi> Nor can this be designed to any other End, but the giving the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> the commendation of Mercy and Moderation above a <hi>Protestant Church.</hi> For as 'tis certain, that the <hi>one Law</hi> of burning and extirpating Hereticks, was a thousand fold worse, and hath produced infinitely more Sanguinary effects, than all the Laws and Rigours that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> can be charged with; so there is nothing can be falser, than that either her Principle, or practice, do parralell or justify the barbarous and brutal severities of the <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nch King,</hi> and the <hi>Inquisition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were all <hi>Protestants</hi> agreed that Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in meer matters of Religion should be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately granted in a Legal way; yet I do not see how the <hi>Papists</hi> should pretend to any benefit by it, or be able to lay a just claim to a share in it. So that the foundation which Mr. <hi>Pen</hi> goes upon, of mens having a Right to be indulged in matters of Religion, is too narrow to support the stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture he raiseth upon it. For tho' there may be somethings retained in <hi>Popery,</hi> which may be called matters of Religion; yet in the bulk and complex of it, it is a Conjuration against all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and a Conspiracy against the Peace of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, and the Rights of Mankind. 'Tis one of the Crimes as well as Miseries of this Age, that out of a dread of some, and in complacence to others, we have avoided representing <hi>Popery</hi> in its native colours, and calling it by the Names properly due into it. But I have alway's thought, that 'tis better faile in our Courtship to men, than in our duty to God, and fidelity to the Interest of Jesus Christ, and the safety of mankind. Nor do I doubt but that they will be better approved in the great day of account, who Character Persons, Doctrines, and Practices as the Scripture doth, than they, who that they may accomodate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves unto, and be acceptable with the world, speak of them in a softer stile. Now if either Blasphemies against God, or Tyrannies over men; if either the defacing the <hi>Ideas</hi> of a Deity, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting the Principles of vertu, and moral Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty; if either the subverting the foundations of natural Religion, or the overthrowing the most essential Articles of the Christian Faith; if either the most avowed and bold affronts offred to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or the bloodiest and most brutal outrages executed against the best of men; if all these be sufficient to preclude a party from the benefit of Liberty due to people in Religious matters, I am sure, none have reason to challeng it in behalf of the <hi>Papists,</hi> nor cause to complain, if it be denied them. Can there be any thing more unreasonable, than that they should claim a <hi>Toleration</hi> in a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant State,</hi> whose Principles not only allow, but oblige them to destroy us, as soon as their power inables them to do it? Is not the Doctrine of the <hi>Popes</hi> Supremacy, and his having a Right to <hi>Depose Kings,</hi> and absolve Subjects from their Allegiance, together with that of breaking Faith to Hereticks, and the extirpating all those who cannot believe as the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> doth, mighty inducements to those whom they have baptized with that name, and to whom they long to exercise that courtesie, for the Repealing of the <hi>Penal</hi> and <hi>Test Laws</hi> against <hi>Papists?</hi> Nor a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e these Principles falsely charged upon them, but they are the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Decisions of their General <hi>Councils</hi> and <hi>Popes,</hi> whom they stile Infallible. So that Mr. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Book</hi> and <hi>Letters,</hi> which seem to have been written not so much in favour of Dissenting <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants,</hi> as of <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> can little advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage the latter, even allowing the Principle which he goes upon, and admitting all he hath said for mens Right to Liberty in meer matters of Religion, to be unanswerable. And his telling us (<hi>Good Adv. p.</hi> 42.) <hi>that Violence and Tyranny are not natural cons<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quences of Popery,</hi> do's only discover his kindness to <hi>Rome,</hi> and the little Friendship and care he hath for the <hi>Protestant</hi> Interest. For we know both the Principles of their Religion too well, and have at all times experienced, and do at this day feel the effects of them too sensibly, to be deluded by this kind of Sophistry, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed upon by so palpable a Falsehood, to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the means of our safety. Wheresoever any <hi>Popish Rulers</hi> Act with Gentlness and Moderation towards those whom their Church hath declared <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>icks,</hi> 'tis either because there are Political Reasons for it, as might be easily shewed in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to all those States and Governments which he mentions, or because there are some <hi>Princes</hi> of the <hi>Roman Communion,</hi> in whom the Dictates of Humane Nature are more prevalent than those of their Religion.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:187986:5"/>
            <p>But should the gentle Temper of the English Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, sway them beyond the strict obligations of duty, and make them willing to Repeal the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> against <hi>Papists;</hi> yet to do it in their present Circumstances, and at such a conjuncture as this, were the highest act of folly in the world, and a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying both their own safety and that of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion▪ Had the Roman Catholicks forbore to assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me a liberty till it had been legally given them; they had been the more capable objects of such a Grace; but to bestow it upon them after they have in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and defiance of all our Laws taken it, 'twere to justify their usurpation, and approve their crime. Could they have been contented with the private practice of their worship, and the nonexaction of the penalties to which our Statutes make them lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, without leaping into all offices of Trust and Command, and invading our Seats of judicature, our Churches, and our Universities; their mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty might have wrought much upon the generosity &amp; candor of all sort of Protestants; but their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious wresting all power into their hands, and their laying aside all those that have either any zeal for our Civil Rights or for the Protestant Religion, is enough to kindle our further indignation, in stead of influencing us to thoughts of moderation &amp; leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And should we once begin to cancel our Laws, according to the measure and proportion, that they break them and usurp upon them, no man can tell where that will terminate; and they will be sure to turn it into an encouragement to further attempts. For having in compliance with their impudence, and to absolve them from the guilt of their crimes and Treasons, abrogated the Laws against popery, they will not faile in a little while to betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the same Methods, for obtaining the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition of all the Laws for Protestancy. 'Tis but for the King to declare, that he will have all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to be of his own Religion; and then by the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick of the late Cant which he used in his Speech to the Council at <hi>Windsor, that they who are not for him are against him;</hi> we must immediately either turn papists, or be put in to the same list with them, &amp; be thought worthy of the same Royal Displeasure, which they are become obnoxious unto, who can not find it to be their duty and interest to destroy the <hi>Tests.</hi> And <hi>Mr. Pen's</hi> argument of <hi>being afraid of his Majesties &amp; the Papists Power, &amp; yet to provoke it,</hi> (Good Adv. p. 43.) will hold in the one case as well as in the other. Nor do I see but that the court may improve an other Topick of his against us (ibid. p. 44.) viz. that we <hi>were ill Courtiers by setting him up, first to give him Roast meat, and then to beat him with the Spit,</hi> by refusing to be of his Religion. To which I may add, that the brutal severities exercised towards <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Piedmont,</hi> are but ill inducements to prevaile upon a Reformed Nation to give liberty to Papists. 'Tis an axiom founded in the light of Nature, as well as an Oracle of Revelation, <hi>that with what measure any do mete unto others, it shall be measured to them again; and that whatsoever any would that we should do to them, they should do so to us.</hi> Would the Papists once perswade Catholick Rulers to give indulgence to those of our Religion; it would be an argument that they acted sincerely in their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding against <hi>Penal Laws</hi> for matters of Religion; and would mightily provaile upon all of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Communion to Repeal such statues as are Enacted against them. But while they continue and increase their persecution against us in all places where they have power; I do not see how they can reasonably expect, that we should believe them either to be just or honest, or to deserve any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of lenity. <hi>Reprizals</hi> are the only methods, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby to bring them to peaceable and equal Terms. Had protestant Princes &amp; States, given Papal Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes to understand, that they would act upon the same square that they do, and retaliate upon those of the Romish Faith, whatsoever should be inflicted because of Religion upon those af ours; I have ground to think that the <hi>Clergy</hi> in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> would have had more discretion, than to have been Instrumental in stirring up the late persecutions, &amp; of instigating Rulers to such unparralelled barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. 'Tis not many years since a Prince in Germany begun to treat protestants with an unjust severity, and to banish them his Countrey, contrary to his word, and the stipulation he had made with them; but upon the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Brandeburgs</hi> both threatning &amp; beginning to do so by the Roman Catholicks in his Dutchy of <hi>Cleve,</hi> the other Prince immediately fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare his rigour, and the Protestants had fair Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter allowed them. And therefore if <hi>Mr. Pen</hi> and his Catholick friends, instead of reproaching the Church of England <hi>of justifying by her principle the King of France and the Inquisition,</hi> would prevaile for abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishing the one and for putting an end to persecution by the other, they would thereby do more for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining the Nations to Tolerate papists, than either by all their invidious <hi>Satyr's</hi> against the conformable Clergy, or by their <hi>Panegyricks</hi> upon a Popish Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch and the Romish Church. In the mean time, 'tis most unreasonable for them to demand or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, and unwise as well as unseasonable, for Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish protestants to consent to the abrogation of the <hi>Tests,</hi> and the Repealing of the <hi>Penal</hi> Laws against papists. Moreover tho' 'tis possible that we might defend our selves against the dangers that might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue upon it, had we a prince of our own Religion on the Throne, yet it would be to surrender our selves unto their power, and to expose our selves to their Discretion, should we venture to do it while a Papist of his Majesties humour hath the weilding of the Scepter. One of the main argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by which <hi>Mr. Pen</hi> would perswade us against all apprehension of danger from the <hi>Papis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:187986:6"/> in case the <hi>Test</hi> and <hi>Penal</hi> Laws were abolished, is the inconsiderableness of ther number in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of Protestants, (Good Adv. p. 49.) And yet if there be so many ill men in the Nation, as he inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates (<hi>Letter</hi> 3d. <hi>p.</hi> 12) who being of no Religion, are ready upon the motives of wordly interest, to take upon them the profession of any, were it not for fear of being at one time or an other called to an account: I do not see but that as the Papists through having the King on their side, are already possessed of what he stiles the <hi>Artificial</hi> strength of the Kingdom, why they may not in a short while, were those Laws once destroyed by which the Atheistical and profane sort of men are kept in aw', come to obtain too much of the <hi>natural</hi> strenth of it, and raise their number to a nearer equality to that of Protestants. And tho' they should never multiply to any near proportion, yet we may easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagine, what a few hands may be able to do, when authorized by a popish Soveraign, and secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by a well disciplined Army commanded by Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks, could they once get to have a share in the Legislation, and to be legally stated in all places of Trust and Power. What need we had of a legal security for our Religion, in case of a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists coming to inherit the Crown, not only the late King who thorowly knew his Brothers temper and bigottry, but those Loyal Zealots who with an unhappy vigour opposed the Bill of Exclusion, were sensible of; and therefore besides all the security which we have for our Religion by the Statutes in Force, they offered many other provisions for its protection, and several of them very threatning to the Monarchy, which we might have had estab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed into Laws, if through our persuite of the point of Exclusion, we had not been so improvident as to despise and reject them. He that dares attempt so much as he hath done, in opposition unto and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance of all our Laws; what will he not have the confidence to undertake, and be in a condition to accomplish, if these obstructions were out of his way. The penal Laws can not prejudice the Papists in this Kings Reign, seeing he can connive at the non-execution of them; and the Repeal of them now, can not benefit the Papists when he is gone, because if they do not be have themselves modestly, we can either reestablish them, or enact others which they will be as little fond of. But their abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation at this time, would infallibly prejudice us, and would prove to be the pulling up of the Sluces and the throwing down the Dikes, which stemm the deludg that is breaking in upon us, and which hinder the threatning waves from overflowing us. And whereas <hi>Mr. Pen</hi> would obtrude upon weak and credulous men, <hi>that if these Laws were Repealed, the King is willing to give us other for our security, and that he would only exchange the security, and not destroy it, (Letter</hi> 2d <hi>p.</hi> 11.) he must pardon us, if we do not easily believe him, after what we know of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties natural Genius, and Religious Bigottry, and after what we have seen and experienced in the whole course of his Government. And if there be no other way of <hi>giving the King an opportunity of Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his word with the Church of England,</hi> in preserving her and maintaining our Religion, but the Repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the <hi>Penal</hi> and <hi>Tests Laws,</hi> as he intimates unto us (<hi>Good Adv. p.</hi> 50.) we have not found the Royal Faith so sacred and inviolable in other instances, as to rob our selves of a Legal defence and protection, for to depend upon the precarious one of a bare promise, which his <hi>Ghostly</hi> Fathers, whensoever they find it convenient, will tell him it was unlawful to make, and which he can have a Dispensation for the breaking of, at what time he pleaseth. Nor do we remember, that when he pledged his Fath unto us in so many promises, that the parting with our Laws was declared to be the condition upon which he made and undertook to perform them. Neither can any have the confidence to alledg it, without having recourse to the Papal doctrine of <hi>Mental Reservation.</hi> Which being one of the principles of that <hi>Order</hi> under whose conduct he is, makes us justly affray'd to rely upon his word without further security. However we do hereby see with what little sincerity <hi>Mr. Pen</hi> writes: and what small regard he hath to his Majesties honor, when he tells the Church of England, <hi>that if She please</hi> and like the Terms of giving up the <hi>Penal</hi> and <hi>Test</hi> Laws against Papists, that then the <hi>King will perform his word with her</hi> (Good Adv. p. 17.) but that otherway's, it is <hi>She who breaks with him, and not he with her. (ibid. p.</hi> 44.)</p>
            <p>Tho something may be said, for the Repealing of all <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> in reference to every perswasion that is called Religion, how incongruously soever it may claim that Name; yet 'tis inconsistent with the safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all Civil Government, and a plain betraying of the Civil Liberties, as well as the established Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in great <hi>Brittain,</hi> not to allow the procluding those from places of Trust, of whose fidelity we can have no assurance. And therefore as all that <hi>Mr. Pen</hi> hath alledged for abolishing the <hi>Tests</hi> is miserably silly; so he hath thereby too manifestly detected the small regard he bears to the safety of the Kingdoms and the Protestant cause, not to be suspected in every thing else which he hath more plausibly and reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly asserted. For as all Governments have an unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionable Right to use means whereby to preserve themselves; so 'tis not only lawful but expedient that they should have <hi>Tests,</hi> by which it may be known, who are fit to be trusted with the Legislative &amp; Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power. Without this, no Constitution can subsist, nor Subjects be in any security under it. Neither can any Reasons be advanced against the <hi>Test</hi> Laws, but what are of equal force against exacting oaths of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:187986:7"/> and promises of Fidelity from those, whom the Government thinks meets to Employ. One might think, that <hi>Mr. Pen</hi> should allow as much to the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as he challengeth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in his Government of <hi>Pensiluania.</hi> For I find that not only such shall be precluded from a share in the Government there, <hi>who shall either be convicted of ill Fame and unsober Conversation, or who shall not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg Iesus Christ to be the Son of God, and Saviour of the world, (Chap.</hi> 2d. <hi>of their Constitutions and Laws)</hi> but that <hi>none shall be either chosen into Office, or so much as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to chuse, but who solemnly declare and promise fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to William Pen and his Heirs:</hi> (Chap. 57.) This I take not only to be equivalent unto, but something more than our <hi>Tests</hi> do amount unto. For whereas there may be several whom the <hi>Quakers</hi> may judg persons <hi>of unsober Conversation;</hi> who may be true to the Civil Interest of their Country, and willing to the utmost of their power, to preserve the peace and promote the prosperity of it; we have no ground to believe the like of <hi>Papists</hi> in relation to the welfare and safety of a Protestant State. And that not only because they acknowledg a forraign Jurisdiction in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>consistent with and paramount to ours; but because they are obliged by the principles of their Religion, whensoever they find themselves able, to destroy and extirpate us. I'm sure that the Motives which in 73, and 78 enforced to the Enacting of the <hi>Test</hi> Laws, do at this season plead more effectually for the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueing them. Nor had we so much cause then of being afraid of Popery, or to be apprehensive of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our Religion overturned by Papists, which were the Inducements to the making of thes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; as we have ground to dread it at this time, and to be jealows of it under the present conjuncture. And the more that the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and their <hi>Advocates,</hi> press to have these Laws abolished, the more fear they excite in us of their design, if they knew how to effect it, and make us the more resolved to hazard all we have to maintain them. For as no Papist is prejudiced by them in his person or property; so they are the most innocent and moderate security we can have for the preservation of our selves and of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Nor could any thing justify the Wisdom of the Nation in being without them so long, but that we were not till then suspitious of the Religion, of the Regnant Prince, nor apprehensive before of the misfortune of having a Popish successor. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reas <hi>Mr. Pen</hi> tells us, that <hi>it were ridiculous to talk of giving liberty of Conscience, and at the same time imagine that the Tests ought to be continued: (Good Adv. p.</hi> 59.) We may not only reply, that Liberty of Conscience has no Relation to mens being admitted unto Civil Trusts, but that the same is practiced in several sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and Governments both Popish and Protestant, and in <hi>Pensilvania</hi> it self, where I suppose Liberty of Conscience is allowed. For as we find freedom wouchsaved ro men in matters of Religion both in <hi>Holland,</hi> and in diverse protestant States in Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, without their being capable of Claiming a share in the Magistracy; so tho' the Protestant Religion be tolerated in <hi>Collen,</hi> yet it is with a preclusion of all of that Religion from Authority. Whatsoever else <hi>Mr. Pen</hi> say's upon this head, is so despicably weak that as I neither judg it worthy to be taken notice of, nor have Room to do it; so I am confident that be his Religion what it will, which by reason of his late Papers I have more Reason to suspect than ever, he writes as much against his conscience and judgment, as again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Pattern and example which he hath sett us in <hi>Pensilvania.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confess the Dissenters, are under more tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, than other Protestants, to wish for, and to endeavour the abrogation of the Penal Laws. And as this makes them to be the more particularly applied unto by the Court for the promoting of it; so it ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them the more liable to be influenced by Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courses of the nature and complexion that <hi>Mr. Pen's</hi> are of. But I hope they will consider, that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of the Protestant Religion to themsel'ves, their posterity, and the Kingdom; is more valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than a little temporal ease, and which they only hold by the precarious tenure of the Kings word. Surely they can not be so infatuated as to think that the Papists love them, or that they will trust them any longer, than they have occasion to use them. I would think, that it should both make them blush to find themselves cupled with Roman Catholiks in courts and Employments, while their follow Protestants are shut out, and make them jealous that they are only made use of for some mischievous and sinistruous e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> They can never hope to lay such a merit u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Court, as the Church of England hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; and her reward may fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn them wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey are to expect, when they have done the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>b that is allotted for them. His Majesties sir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ty in giving liberty to Dissenting protestants, may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e easily guessed at, by his ordering 26, <hi>poor Scotts Dissenters</hi> to be sent to the <hi>Barbados</hi> for slaves; and this both since the Emitting of his <hi>first Proclamation for a Toleration,</hi> and without the having any thing objected to them, but what concerned their Consciences in matters of Religion. The Terms upon which Phanaticks are to enjoy his Majesties favour and how long they are to expect the continuance of that mighty Grace, we have declared by himself, as they stand recorded in my Lord <hi>Melfort's Letter to the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytrian Ministers in Scotland.</hi> Namely <hi>that he intends to continue their liberty, if he have sutable encouragement and concurrence from them in their Doctrine and practice, and if they concurr with him in removing of the penal laws.</hi> This is the Task that they are indulged and preferred for, and 'tis a wonder they do not foresee that their destiny will be one and the same, in case they have once done it, as if they do it not. This is the Fountain of all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:187986:8"/> his Majesties friendship to them; and the glorious as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion of its having been alway's <hi>his principle that Conscience ought not to be constrained, and that none ought to be persecuted for meer matters of Religion,</hi> is at last dwindled into this, that he will give them liberty so long as they will concurr and cooperate with him in his introducing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f popery, and till they have destroyed the Laws by which our own Religion is fenced about and defended. Certainly 'tis high time to consider, what this is which is exacted of them, and what hazard they not only expose the Nation and the Gospel unto, but what guilt they derive upon themselves if they undertake and pursue it. Nor can they promote th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ealing of the <hi>Penal</hi> Laws against Papists, and the <hi>Test</hi> Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out running themselves under the guilt of perjury, and the making themselves chargeable before God, with all the blood that was shed in the war between King Charles the first and the Parliament. For an one of the Articles of the <hi>solemn League and covenant,</hi> was to endeavour to extirpate popery; so the countenance and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which that Prince gave to Papists, was a main in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient in the State of the Quarrel for which they drew their swords against him, and in the assertion whereof so many thousands lost their lives. Can they now be willing to act in direct opposition to that <hi>Covenant</hi> which rather than renounce and disclaim the obligatory force of, many of them have suffered so much? or would they have the guilt of all the blood lye upon them which was shed in the former long and fatal war? I'm perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that many, who are most foreward, to persue the abrogation of the <hi>Tests</hi> and <hi>penal</hi> Laws against Papists, never gave themselves leave to think what they are hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried unto. <hi>Mr. Pen</hi> tels them, he will begg them <hi>for fools, if they do it not</hi> (Good <hi>Adv.</hi> p. 54.) and I darc take upon me to say, that they are most execrable knaves and villaines, if they do it. Is it possible they should be so deprived of al understanding, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to perceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves meerly trick't upon, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> use of for Tools to promote a design which other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>e the wisdom and integrity not to be Instrumental in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>hen <hi>Jeffries</hi> who a while ago' said on the <hi>Bench, she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Fanatick, and I will shew you a knave, and that 'twa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ossible to be a Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and not to be a Rebel;</hi> should now caress them as his Majesties best and most Loyal Subjects, and tell them upon their being advance to Offices, that <hi>he is glade to find honest men come to be employed,</hi> which was the complement he late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bestowed upon <hi>Sr John Shorter.</hi> 'Tis likely they may be told, that if they will fall in with the Papists for destroying the Church of England, that they shall be secured from the Resentments of the next <hi>Heir,</hi> by having the Monarchy made dissolvable into a Republick upon his Majesties death. And this would seem to be what <hi>Mr. Pen</hi> intends, when the tells us, that such a <hi>Bargain will be driven with the Kingdom, as will make the Church of England think that half a loaf had been better than no bread; (good Adv. p.</hi> 43.) <hi>and that one year</hi> will show <hi>the trick, and mightily deceive her▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d the opportunity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> being preserved lost, and an other bargain driven mightily to her disadvantage. ibid. p.</hi> 42.) But as it will be impossible for Papists and Dissenters, should they conspire together, to be able to effect it, considering the interest which her integrity in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion, and her tenderness for the Rights and Liberties of the Kingdoms, have justly acquired unto her; so it were both the most foolish as well as criminal thing, which any pretending themselves Protestants can be guilty of, to be in any measure accessory unto it. For as there is nothing in reference to their own Religious liberties, and the priviledges of the Nation, which they may not undoubtedly expect, from her justice as well as from her mercy and moderation; so there is no means left within our vieu, either to give a lasting Peace and a firm settlement to three distracted Kingdoms, or to bring the Protestant interest into such a condition as may ballance the Papal grandure in Europe, and give check to the rage of persecution in all places, but her happy advancement to the Thrones of great Brittain and Ireland▪ when it shall ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his Majesty. Untill which time, I hope all who call themselves Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, will submit to the worst of fate, rather than to fall under the curse of this Age, and ignominy with all that shall come after, for becoming an united party with the Church of Rome, in any of her designes how plausible soever they may appear.</p>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:187986:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:187986:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:187986:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:187986:11"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:187986:11"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:187986:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:187986:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:187986:13"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>